Okay, so we're up to today's דף, Daf, דף ג Daf Gimmel
in עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, at the bottom of עמוד ב, Amud
Bet, in the middle of the opening אגדתא. Aggadata. The opening אגדתא
Aggadata is significant because it is framing, meaning like a general question
in this מסכת Masechet is what is the rabbis' attitude towards, you
know, non-Jews and the non-Jewish world and so on. So this opening
אגדתא Aggadata talks about like in the future all of the, you
know, God will sort of hold a day of court, take court,
day of judgment, and all of the non-Jews will come and try
to justify their actions and say they were all doing it, they're
all connected to the תורה, Torah, they're all doing it for the
sake of allowing the Jews to learn תורה. Torah. And God will
reject it all. So it's important in a couple of ways. Number
one, and I think I failed to mention this yesterday, you know,
it's interesting in the opening of the tractate of עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah that these nations are not being held accountable for their idolatry.
It's not like if you look in the תורה, Torah, right, in
the תורה Torah the big point is that, you know, it's sort
of the belief in a single transcendent, you know, God who is
not worshipped through images, you know, and coming against all of the
idolatry of the nations, right, and they go into the land and
the concern is that the people of the land will lead you
astray with their idolatry. It's all about the war against idolatry. And
the verse in ישעיהו Yeshayahu which is being quoted here as the
basis for this מדרש Midrash is all about in the future, you
know, all of the idols will be shown to be falsehoods. But
by the time the rabbis, it wasn't about idolatry, right, it was
about the other religions, although here you don't even hear them debating
about the other religions. It's really completely framed in like a sort
of a different type of a way, but it is certainly not
about idolatry. It's about have you kept the מצוות Mitzvos and the
תורה, Torah, are you connected to the מצוות Mitzvos and the תורה
Torah or not. So it's about like what does it mean to
have the Jewish religion taking that into the larger world and so
on.
The מהרש״א Maharsha actually says that the image of, you know, it
says he got a ספר תורה Sefer Torah in his bosom. He
sort of, the מהרש״א Maharsha says that the image of this was
that, you know, everybody wants to say my faith is the true
faith. So in the future times, you know, God reveals God's self
and says okay, which is the ספר Sefer that God is holding
hidden, you know, which is the faith that is closest to God,
that is the true faith. Oh, it's the תורה Torah that's in
God's bosom, not our faith is the true faith. But the point
is again that it's not really about idolatry, right, it's about a
life of תורה Torah and מצוות. Mitzvos. So that's sort of number
one. And then number two is the question about do you sort
of give recognition to the accomplishments of the nations, of the, you
know, larger world, you know, the roads and the bridges and the
bathhouses and the markets and all of that. So in this מדרש,
Midrash, right, the nations are quoted as saying that, so it's sort
of being acknowledged, but it's being acknowledged in order to be dismissed.
It's dismissed because you did it for your own sake, which doesn't
mean that it's not a positive thing that we can benefit from,
but that's the basis for dismissing it. And it's being dismissed because
it's ultimately God says anyway I do it all, it's all mine
anyway. Okay, so this opening again is important for two themes
in this opening מדרש, Midrash, right, number one to see that the
fight is not about idolatry, it's about who's connected to the תורה
Torah and not connected to the תורה. Torah. And also the way
of it sort of dismissing the accomplishments of the other nations. Okay,
so now we pick up the דף. Daf. Okay, so it says
so all the nations come and God rejects them all. So אומרים
לפניו, Omrim Lefanav, we are now about fifteen lines from the bottom,
beginning of the line אומרים לפניו Omrim Lefanav right over where it
says דברים לג. Dvarim Lamed Gimmel. So אומרים לפניו, Omrim Lefanav,
the nations now say to God, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono Shel Olam,
Master of the Universe, כלום נתתה לנו ולא קיבלנוה? Klum Nesata Lanu
V'lo Kiblanuha?
How are you blaming us for not observing the תורה Torah and
we're being held responsible for not keeping the תורה, Torah, but you
never gave it to us? Okay, had you given it to us
we would have accepted it. So God says what? Don't you know
the famous מדרש? Midrash? So God says back to them, ומי מצי
למימר הכי? U'mi Matzi L'meimar Hachi? So then the גמרא Gemara intervening,
how could they say such a claim? והכתיב, V'hachtiv, the verse says,
ויאמר ה׳ מסיני בא, Vayomar Hashem MiSinai Ba, God came from Sinai,
וזרח משעיר למו, V'zarach MiSeir Lamo, He came from שעיר, Seir, וכתיב
אלוה מתימן יבוא, U'chtiv Eloah MiTeiman Yavo, and He came from תימן.
Teiman. מאי בעי בשעיר מאי בעי בפארן? Mai Ba'ei B'Seir Mai Ba'ei
B'Paran? What's he doing in שעיר Seir and what's he doing at
פארן? Paran? שעיר Seir is the place of עשו, Esav, פארן Paran
is the place of ישמעאל. Yishmael. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
ללמד שהחזירה, Lelamed SheHechizira, הקדוש ברוך הוא, Hakadosh Baruch Hu, God
before giving the תורה Torah to the Jews, he brought it around,
he shopped it around to כל אומה ולשון. Kol Uma V'Lashon. Okay,
ולא קיבלוה, V'Lo Kibluha, and
they didn't accept it, עד שבא לישראל, Ad SheBa L'Yisrael,
until he came to ישראל, Yisrael, וקיבלוה, V'Kibluha, and they accepted it.
So how can they say to God, God it's not fair you
never offered it to us? According to the מדרש Midrash you were
offered it. אלא הכי אמרי, Ela Hachi Amri, this is what they
say to Him: כלום קיבלנוה ולא קיימנוה? Klum Kiblanuha V'lo Kiyamanuha?
If you would have only given it to us, we would have
fulfilled it. So okay, maybe we made a mistake, we didn't accept
it, but still it's not fair to hold us responsible for not
living a life of תורה Torah and מצוות, Mitzvos, had you given
it to us, we would have accepted it. So the גמרא Gemara
says what? על דא תבריתוהו, Al Da'at Tavar Tuhu, this is their
like this is... shatters them, meaning this claim, you know,
obviously undermines them. What type of what type of claim is that?
אמאי לא קבלתוה? Amai lo kibalatuhu? You can't say, oh, had you
only given it to me, I would have accepted it. You should
have accepted it! I would have fulfilled it. You should have accepted
it! It was offered to you. You can't say, well, even though
I didn't accept it, I would have done it had I accepted
it. You know? You didn't accept it! So oh, no, okay fine.
אלא כך אמרו לפניו, Ela kach amru lefanav, fine. Here's what they
said to him. רבונו של עולם, Ribono shel olam, Master of the
Universe. כלום כפית עלינו הר כגיגית ולא קבלנוה? Clum kafita aleinu har
k'gigis v'lo kibalnuha?
That's not fair! You know, we... okay, is it true we did
not willingly accept it? Sure. But you know who else didn't willingly
accept it? The Jews! You had a whole mountaintop over them. So
if you would have forced us like you forced them, we would
have committed ourselves to a life of תורה ומצוות. Torah u'mitzvos. All
right, whatever. כמו שעשית לישראל דכתיב ויתיצבו בתחתית ההר. K'mo she'asisa l'Yisroel
d'chsiv v'yisyatzvu b'sachtis ha'har.
They stood underneath the mountain. ואמר רב דימי בר חמא מלמד שכפה
הקדוש ברוך הוא הר כגיגית V'amar Rav Dimi bar Chama melamed she'kafa
HaKadosh Baruch Hu har k'gigis and G-d held the mountain like a
barrel על ישראל al Yisroel over the Jewish people ואמר להם אם
אתם מקבלים את התורה מוטב ואם לאו שם תהא קבורתכם. v'amar lahem
im atem m'kablim es haTorah mutav v'im lav sham t'hei kvuraschem. And
He said to them, if you accept the Torah, good. And if
not, this... this will be where you get buried. מיד אמר להם.
Miyad amar lahem. Okay. So that's their claim. The claim is, G-d,
had You only forced it upon us, You were... You know, You
still played favorites. You gave it to the Jews, You forced it
on them. Okay, we didn't willingly accept it, but you know, You
could have forced it on us too and then we would have
lived a life of תורה ומצוות. Torah u'mitzvos. So אמר להם הקדוש
ברוך הוא, amar lahem HaKadosh Baruch Hu, so G-d says to them,
הראשונות ישמיעונו. Harishonos yashmiunu. Now going back to quoting the פסוק pasuk
because all of this is a מדרש midrash which is interpreting the
various words of these verses in ישעיה. Yeshaya. So G-d says to
them, הראשונות ישמיעונו. Harishonos yashmiunu. Again,
from the verse in ישעיה. Yeshaya. So what does that mean? Let's
look at the early stuff and then let's see whether your claim
that you would have lived a life of תורה ומצוות Torah u'mitzvos
had it been forced upon you holds water. Because let's look at
the מצוות mitzvos that you were given and see how well you
did with
those. Well, G-d... we weren't forced to do the מצוות, mitzvos, we
were just
forcibly given them. Okay, and then we lived a life of תורה
ומצוות. Torah u'mitzvos. So you were given the שבע מצוות בני נח.
Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach. שבע מצוות. Sheva Mitzvos. It doesn't matter. We
were given them. שבע מצוות שקבלתם היכן קיימתם. Sheva Mitzvos she'kibaltem heichan
kiyamtem.
The seven מצוות mitzvos that you did accept, well let's, you know,
let's see what your track record was. Okay, so therefore obviously you
have shown that even after being given מצוות mitzvos by G-d, it
did not translate into you living up to them. So you can't
come and claim that had you only been given the תורה, Torah,
you would have lived up to it.
We didn't live up to the תורה Torah too, unfortunately.
All right, well we did better than that. ומנלן דלא קיימו? U'minalan
d'lo kiyamu? And now where do you know that the nations did
not fulfill the שבע מצוות בני נח? Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach? So
by the way, notice where this מדרש midrash is going. Like first
we establish that they did not live a life connected to תורה
ומצוות Torah u'mitzvos or even indirectly supporting our life of תורה ומצוות.
Torah u'mitzvos. And now we're saying and they didn't even live up
to some basic, you know, sort of
religious minimums or religious ethical minimums of living. You know, even the
שבע מצוות בני נח Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach they didn't live up
to.
Is that why we shouldn't consider them back?
But then the דתני רב יוסף, D'tani Rav Yosef, no, but you
came a little late, but the point is it's not exactly saying
that this is the basis for the תקנות, takanos, but it's still
important that this is how the opening סוגיא sugya framing this tractate
is shaping a way of perceiving the larger world, which is not
a one-to-one correspondence with certain תקנות, takanos, but it's important because that's
what this tractate is. How do we negotiate that larger world? An
important question is how do we even... how do we perceive it
in general? Now this is not the only מדרש. midrash. We will
hear other voices as well. But right now this is like dismissive
of their accomplishments, as I said before. It's not framing things as
about idolatry versus belief in G-d. It's about a like religious life,
a life of תורה ומצוות, Torah u'mitzvos, which is our life, it's
not their life. That's how it's being framed. And even they didn't
even fulfill our minimum type of a one. ומנלן דלא קיימו? U'minalan
d'lo kiyamu?
Where do we see they did not fulfill it? דתני רב יוסף
עמד וימודד ארץ. D'tani Rav Yosef amad vayimodad eretz. Now we're going
to a different verse. We've been focusing on the verse in ישעיה
מ"ג, Yeshaya mem gimmel, now going to the verse in חבקוק. Chabakuk.
עמד וימודד ארץ ראה ויתר גוים. Amad vayimodad eretz ra'ah vayater goyim.
G-d stood up and He measured out the land. He saw and
He like permitted the nations, it's how it's being read. Literally ראה
ויתר. ra'ah vayater. Is it like...
like loosened the nations? Right, but it's read like the word מותר,
mutar, permitted. So what does that mean? מה ראה? Mah ra'ah? What
did G-d see? ראה שבע מצוות שקיבלו עליהם בני נח. Ra'ah sheva
mitzvos she'kiblu aleihem bnei Noach. G-d looked at the seven מצוות mitzvos
that they did accept upon themselves. It's interesting phrase, שקיבלו עליהם, she'kiblu
aleihem, they accepted. Like going back to the whole הר כגיגית har
k'gigis story, like they never accepted, G-d just commanded them. But okay,
anyway, the שבע מצוות בני נח sheva mitzvos bnei Noach were commanded
ולא קיימום v'lo kiyamum and He saw that they didn't. So He
took stock of the land, He saw they weren't fulfilling even the
basic seven נח'י Noachi מצוות. mitzvos. עמד והתירן להם. Amad v'hitiran lahem.
And therefore He said, forget it, it's all permissible. So now that's
a... now that's a different דרשה, drasha, we're just bringing it in
as an aside to demonstrate that this מדרש midrash shows that from
the מדרש'ס midrash's perspective, they did not fulfill the seven. מצוות בני
נח. mitzvos Bnei Noach. But now that we're quoting this מדרש, Midrash,
we have to unpack it. What does it mean that they were
God permitted it to them? אישתרי אישתרי ishtarei ishtarei is just like
coming to like a like you know coming to like like like
are they therefore going to be rewarded because of their you know
because they didn't do it now they're it's permitted to them? אם
כן מצינו חוטא נשכר, im kein matzinu chotei niskar, the sinner is
rewarded. Oh you didn't do it now it's okay it's all permissible
to you. אמר מר בריה דרבינא Amar Mar b'rei d'Ravina no no
no no no. Here's the point. The point is since they didn't
fulfill the seven Noachide mitzvot דף ג עמוד א daf gimmel amud
aleph לומר שאף על פי שמקיימים אותם אין מקבלים עליהם שכר. lomar
she'af al pi she'mekaymim otam ein mekablim aleihem sachar. Even after they
fulfill them because they have now treated it as if they are
not obligated, they're living a life that does not even recognize the
sense of obligation. Right? It's one thing to be the שול shul
I don't go to, like you know
you sort of recognize it but you don't do it. But now
they're living a life that doesn't even recognize the sense of obligation
then when they're doing things they're not doing them out of a
sense of obligation. They're just doing them because I don't know they're
nice happen to be nice people or you know they decided themselves
this was the right way to live. But therefore so since they're
no longer doing things from the orientation of obligation then even if
they do it they don't get they don't get reward. אף על
פי שמקיימים אותם אין מקבלים עליהם שכר. af al pi she'mekaymim otam
ein mekablim aleihem sachar. So the גמרא Gemara says ולא? v'lo? So
what if they're no longer see themselves as obligated? That means they
don't get any reward? והתניא ve-hatanya and we turn in a ברייתא
Braisa היה רבי מאיר אומר מניין שאפילו עובד כוכבים ועוסק בתורה שהוא
ככהן גדול? Hayah Rabbi Meir omer minayin she'afilu oved kochavim ve'osek ba'Torah
shehu k'kohen gadol? How do you know that even a non-Jew who
involves himself in the תורה, Torah, I'm going to go back to
that phrase involves himself in the תורה, Torah, is like a
כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? תלמוד לומר אשר יעשה אותם האדם וחי בהם.
Talmud lomar asher ya'aseh otam ha'adam v'chai bahem. These are the מצוות
mitzvot that a person shall do them and live by them. Okay
so כהנים לויים וישראלים לא נאמר kohanim leviyim v'Yisraelim lo ne'emar doesn't
say כהן Kohen לוי Levi and ישראל Yisroel will do them אלא
האדם ela ha'adam a human. הא למדת שאפילו עובד כוכבים ha lamadeta
she'afilu oved kochavim or a גוי goy ועוסק בתורה הרי הוא ככהן
גדול. ve'osek ba'Torah harei hu k'kohen gadol. Even a non-Jew or I'll
tell you in a minute how you get כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
is like a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. אלא לומר לך ela lomar
lach so you see they do get reward when they do the
מצוות. mitzvot. אלא לומר לך ela lomar lach so rather no what
it's telling you is שאין מקבלים עליהם שכר כמצווה ועושה. she'ein mekablim
aleihem sachar k'metzuveh v'oseh. If they do it they're not rewarded like
one who is commanded and does, they don't get the full reward
if they do the שבע מצוות בני נח sheva mitzvos Bnei Noach
reward coming out of a sense of obligation אלא כמי שאינו מצווה
ועושה. ela k'mi she'eino metzuveh v'oseh. You only get rewarded as if
you are not obligated and doing it. And when you do something
and you're not obligated the reward is not as great. We would
tend to think maybe the reward would be higher you're doing it
even though you're not required. We'll discuss that there's a lot of
things that are packed into these lines but let's just finish first
the train of thought. So therefore the reward you will get since
you're not doing it anymore out of a sense of obligation is
only the lower level of somebody who does something without being obligated.
דאמר רבי חנינא d'amar Rabbi Chanina because רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says
גדול המצווה ועושה יותר ממי שאינו מצווה ועושה. gadol hametzuveh v'oseh yoter
mi-mi she'eino metzuveh v'oseh. Greater is the one who is commanded and
does than the one who is not commanded. So there's a lot
of things that are packed into here. Let me try to point
out some of the some of the key ones. Okay. So number
one the idea right that the גמרא Gemara here is sort of
saying that you know as I said the first thing is that
they're not even doing the basic שבע מצוות בני נח. sheva mitzvos
Bnei Noach. Okay so like sort of you know no credit to
the accomplishment of the non-Jews no credit to their sort of the
moral lives that they live or the religious lives they live they're
not even doing sort of the minimum thing. And like even if
you sort of see them doing some stuff you can be again
like dismissive of it. Yeah but okay basically you know it's very
it's like the lens through which you look at things right? You
could look out on the world and see all the wonderful accomplishments
of the non-Jews. You could look out on the world and see
oh they also live religious moral lives and is it true that
sometimes they don't? Of course. Sometimes as Michael said Jews also don't
always live up to things and so on. Right? But the orientation
here is the opposite. No fundamentally they're not doing anything. And if
you see them doing something it's like אינו מצווה ועושה eino metzuveh
v'oseh it's not coming from a good place they're not going to
get rewarded for it anyway it's an aberration it's an exception and
so on. So there's obviously shaping a very sort of negative you
know type of a perspective. I should say parenthetically that it actually
is interesting that some פוסקים poskim actually go back and read this
דרשה drasha of אמר והתירן להם amar ve-hittiran lahem in a more
פשט pshat way. I'm trying to remember the context but some פוסקים
poskim in dealing with certain הלכות halakhot about attitude towards non-Jews and
basically sort of says look if they you know you can't it's
sort of like the תינוק שנשבה tinok shenishba argument you know by
how you treat like a Jew who is מחלל שבת mechalel Shabbos
you know if you don't know any better you know you really
can't be held responsible. So actually sort of says the same type
of thing with non-Jews like we can't really look at them as
responsible for not doing the שבע מצוות בני נח sheva mitzvos Bnei
Noach because they have no you know you ask non-Jews nowadays they
have no idea that there's any concept of שבע sheva I mean
okay maybe the רבי Rebbe ruined it because he was spread the
whole idea of the you know the לובביטשער רבי Lubavitcher Rebbe sort
of tried to spread the whole idea of getting non-Jews to keep
the seven Noachide mitzvot. But before that you know like who the
heck knew of the idea you know amongst non-Jews that there was
this concept of שבע... sheva... שבע מצוות בני נח. Sheva Mitzvos Bnei
Noach. So quoting this דרשה drasha of עמד והתירן להן amad vehitiran
lahen as a type of a like a תינוק שנשבה, tinok shenishba,
you know, so we can't, so the exact thing that גמרא Gemara
here is rejecting, but actually look more sympathetically. Don't go ahead and
try to cast aspersions they're not doing this. From their perspective, they
were never obligated. They don't know that this is sort of the
way of looking, you know, that to look at things as if
they were obligated in these seven Noachide מצוות. mitzvos. Okay, so that's
parenthetical. But then moving back to the basic sort of thrust here.
Okay, so this מדרש Midrash of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is a
counter-voice to everything that we've been saying until now. Until now we're
saying all the stuff about, eh, they don't do anything and whatever,
be dismissive of anything you see of them. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
actually is saying, you know, non-Jews if they are עוסק בתורה, osek
baTorah, they actually, they're not just unlike, you know, they're like to
get to the highest level, הרי הוא ככהן גדול. harei hu kekohen
gadol. Now the phrase הרי הוא ככהן גדול harei hu kekohen gadol
is an important one because that's borrowed from a famous like דרש
drash which is, you know, like the משנה Mishna in הוריות, Horayos,
it's sort of the anti-hierarchy statement. It's the statement about how like
the idea of תורה Torah creates a meritocracy that sort of violates
the classic class hierarchy that is yes, that is part of the
traditional structure. Right? The traditional structure is כהן, kohen, לוי, Levi, ישראל,
Yisrael, you know, it's got this hierarchy: man, woman, Jew, non-Jew, etc.
Right? So that's a משנה Mishna in הוריות. Horayos. But the end,
that sort of speaks about that hierarchy. But at the end of
the משנה Mishna it says, when is this true? When they're all
equal. But if you have a, yes, somebody who's a תלמיד חכם,
talmid chacham, even a ממזר mamzer who's a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham,
right, who's at the bottom of the class hierarchy, but if he's
at the top of the תורה Torah like hierarchy which is a
meritocracy, it's not a class hierarchy, anybody can do it, right, then
a ממזר תלמיד חכם mamzer talmid chacham comes before כהן גדול עם
הארץ. kohen gadol am ha'aretz. And it uses כהן גדול kohen gadol
as the symbol of the top of the class hierarchy. And it
says תורה Torah completely overrides, you know, that's the power of like
a sort of a society structured around תורה, Torah, post-temple society structured
around תורה Torah is that it overrides all of these class hierarchies.
Okay. And it uses a famous דרשה: drasha: יקרה היא מפנינים. yekarah
hi mipeninim. The תורה Torah is dearer than pearls, which are, you
know, it's יקרה היא מכהן גדול שנכנס לפני ולפנים. yekarah hi mikohen
gadol shenichnas lifnai velifnim. It is dearer even than the כהן גדול
kohen gadol who goes into the innermost sanctum. Okay, so the, so
the תורה Torah says, forget all this classic hierarchy that we normally
have. If you learn תורה, Torah, you shoot to the top. Okay,
that's the only thing, that's ultimately the hierarchy that trumps. Okay, so
therefore what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying is he's taken it
one step even further and saying, and once that's true, you don't
even have to be a Jew. Even a non-Jew who's עוסק בתורה,
osek baTorah, הרי הוא ככהן גדול. harei hu kekohen gadol. Okay, if
you really involve yourself in תורה, Torah, then that ultimately it doesn't
matter, Jew, non-Jew, none of this matters. Then the question is, okay,
okay, that's not, that's not רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that's this מדרש.
Midrash. That's, so this is, so it's very important, like this is
like a very serious counter-voice to everything that's been going on until
now. It limits itself to a non-Jew who's involving himself in תורה.
Torah. It doesn't talk about non-Jews who build bridges and make iPhones,
but you know, but nevertheless, it sort of put it out there
that like, don't look at it, you know, you know, there could
be amongst the non-Jews people that are greater than even, you know,
than Jews or whatever, and it's not, there's something to disrupt this
whole division of the world into Jew and non-Jew and this whole
hierarchy. And actually the מדרש Midrash that this is based on, the,
this comes from a larger דרשה drasha in the ספרי Sifrei I
think, or whatever, it goes on and on with verses like this
and it says, it says, אדם, adam, it says אדם, adam, it
says אדם, adam, as long as you're עוסק בתורה, osek baTorah, you
know, then you're higher than a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. And I
think one of the, one of the most sort of, anyway, powerful
lines from that מדרש Midrash that I remember was it says, the
verse says, you know, שאו שערים ראשיכם, se'u shearim rasheichem, ושאו
פתחי עולם, u-se'u pischei olam, what is it? No, that's מלך הכבוד.
melech hakavod. It's another פסוק. pasuk. Anyway it says, but there's some
פסוק pasuk that says ויבא גוי צדיק. veyavo goy tzaddik. It
says כהנים לויים וישראלים לא נאמר, kohanim leviyim veyisraelim lo ne'emar, אלא
גוי צדיק. ela goy tzaddik. Like a righteous nation, it's really reading
גוי goy as a גוי, goy, as a non-Jew, you know, אפילו
גוי ועוסק בתורה, afilu goy ve'osek baTorah, you know, that, you know,
will enter in. So that, you know, enter into the pearly gates
as it were. So this מדרש Midrash goes on and on reading
verses that say that it doesn't matter if you're a non-Jew. It
says אדם, adam, it says גוי, goy, it says whatever, anybody can
accomplish this. So it's, so the גמרא, Gemara, it's sort of like
introduces this voice, but it introduces this at the outset as a
way of sort of like almost like diffusing it, right? But by
diffusing it by sort of saying, yeah, first of all it doesn't
really mean כהן גדול, kohen gadol, it really means like he's אינו
מצווה ועושה, eino metzuveh ve'oseh, which is exactly against the point of
הרי הוא ככהן גדול harei hu kekohen gadol because the גמרא Gemara
now basically has said, no, no, no, we don't really mean that,
we mean he's like an אינו מצווה ועושה. eino metzuveh ve'oseh. Okay,
and we... sort of have mentioned this radical idea, but we didn't
sort of continue dealing with it, we didn't continue at sort of
like considering the case about a גוי goy that could be like
a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, right? We just sort of have basically
just said, nah, at the end of the day, they don't even
do the שבע מצוות בני נח sheva mitzvot bnei noach and even
if they do them it's like an אינו מצווה ועושה. eino metzuveh
v'oseh. Okay, so here it is sort of the diffusing of this
of this powerful radical different approach of Rabbi Meir. Now Tosafot of
course discusses the question like Michael said that another גמרא Gemara mentions
this approach of Rabbi Meir and doesn't like it because we're supposed
to say a גוי ששבת goy she-shavas is חייב מיתה. chayav misa.
How do you deal with this Rabbi Meir, that it's important for
a גוי goy to be עוסק בתורה osek b'Torah and the גמרא
Gemara basically says it means for him to learn the מצוות mitzvot
of the שבע מצוות בני נח, sheva mitzvot bnei noach, it doesn't
mean to learn the stuff that's ours. You know, goes back and
it's like, this is very disruptive, this דרשה. drasha. So other גמרות
Gemarot like, you know, push back and try to keep things in
their boxes. No, when we're talking about a גוי goy learning תורה,
Torah, first of all, it doesn't really mean a כהן גדול, kohen
gadol, it's אינו מצווה ועושה. eino metzuveh v'oseh. Second of all, it's
not really talking about all תורה, Torah, it's just talking about his
מצווה, mitzvah, not our מצוות, mitzvot, and so on. But okay, but
the real פשט pshat here is that it's a very disruptive, you
know, idea which the גמרא Gemara is sort of mentioning and dismissing.
The other important question is whether עוסק בתורה osek b'Torah means means
doing מצוות mitzvot or does it mean learning תורה. Torah. Okay, so
the the basic point I said to you, right, that about the
כהן גדול kohen gadol is sort of a hierarchy that comes about
learning תורה. Torah. Okay, and עוסק בתורה osek b'Torah often has that
sense. Okay, but another version of this says אפילו גוי ועושה את
התורה, afilu goy v'oseh es ha-Torah, which more reflects the verse of
אשר יעשה אותם האדם וחי בהם. asher ya'aseh osam ha-adam v'chai bahem.
עושה את ה... oseh es ha-...
it's in... I forget wherever this comes from originally, the ספרא Sifra
I think. It's in the ספרא. Sifra.
And that by the way also fits the idea of what do
you call it? אשר יעשה אותם האדם וחי בהם. asher ya'aseh osam
ha-adam v'chai bahem. So based on that, right, so it's... oh, and
I lost my train of thought. אלא גוי ועושה את התורה. elo
goy v'oseh es ha-Torah.
Anyway, so if you say that, right, then it's not... I mean,
oh, that also fits the larger context here of the גמרא, Gemara,
about like the שבע מצוות בני נח. sheva mitzvot bnei noach. What
are the מצוות mitzvot that you're doing? Okay, so that's like a
different question as well, which is are we even saying that a
גוי goy who does מצוות... mitzvot... Like let's say a גוי goy
wants to go ahead and keep שבת, shabbat, wants to go ahead
and take the לולב, lulav, wants to go ahead and put on
תפילין. tefillin. You know, are we saying that, oh, you want to
do that? You know, great, it doesn't matter that you're not... wait,
what? A non-Jew doing that? But I have to tell you, רמב״ם
Rambam actually rules that if a non-Jew does any of the תרי״ג
מצוות, taryag mitzvot, רמב״ם Rambam says, even ברית מילה, bris milah, which
you would think is specifically about the relationship of the Jews to
God, he says he gets reward as an אינו מצווה ועושה. eino
metzuveh v'oseh. So, right? So that... which is actually... so it's not
ככהן גדול, k'kohen gadol, okay? It's the אינו מצווה ועושה, eino metzuveh
v'oseh, but it's אפילו גוי ועושה את התורה. afilu goy v'oseh es
ha-Torah. So that's another important question, whether this is about learning תורה,
Torah, which we know has that idea that learning תורה Torah breaks
all of the classic hierarchies, or is it about just doing מצוות,
mitzvot, which more reflects the verse it's based on and more reflects
the context in which it's being brought into the גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
so those were just a few small points here.
Yes. Two things. You know, one is I mean I like this
other view because I mean you also have plenty of other שלוחי
מלכי מלחמה, shluchei malchei milchama, which is, you know, very disparaging... so
you have
that sort of here. And then we talked about this yesterday,
all these טענות ta'anot of God was saying, oh they're מרחצאות, merchatzaot,
that reminds me of that other גמרא Gemara in שבת, Shabbat, like
you know, when
you had to run away.
So like are they sort of like borrowing from each other, the
מדרשים? midrashim?
Yeah, they're borrowing from the same type of ideas and you know,
Michael is right, there's another גמרא Gemara in שבת Shabbat where one
of the תנאים, tannaim, I think it's רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says
how wonderful are is this nation they've made they've made the מרחצאות,
merchatzaot, they've made the roads, they've made this and then the other
תנא tanna says ah they all just did it for themselves. So
there, you heard both voices, right, those that sort of praised it
and those that disparaged it, and in this... and there are both
voices, like there's a voice of Rabbi Meir that says you could
look at non-Jews and say it's amazing they're even greater than the
כהן גדול kohen gadol if they live a life of either learning
תורה Torah or doing מצוות mitzvot or whatever it is. But the
opening סוגיא sugya here has a very dominant voice that is not
that, that's not a multiplicity of voices but that sort of in
passing folds in those opinions but for the sake of bracketing it
and disparaging it. Yeah, and putting it all in the words mouth
of God, yeah.
Just on that other the story of שמעון בר יוחאי Shimon bar
Yochai who says right they just did it for themselves.
Assuming they knew about the story right from here and from there
they God's voice here is שמעון בר יוחאי's Shimon bar Yochai voice.
Right, right, right, which is very interesting. Right, but I don't think
that the story in שבת Shabbat knew these two opinions and said
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is going against the God's voice of this
story. I think it sort of goes the opposite, that you actually
had different opinions among the Rabbis and the author of this מדרש
midrash is embracing this one here, the רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon voice,
which is the disparaging one and putting
the רבי שמעון... Rabbi Shimon... but what this opening מדרש midrash is
doing, okay. But you do have this position here, but you do
have this position here of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says that
like even a non-Jew who either is learns תורה Torah or does
תורה, Torah, does
מצוות, mitzvot, jumps to the very top of the hierarchy, but in
the end the גמרא Gemara says, yeah, they don't even do their
שבע מצוות sheva mitzvot and even if they do them, they only
get reward of אינו מצווה ועושה. eino metzuveh ve’oseh. But again, as
I said, it's fascinating that רמב"ם Rambam rules that a non-Jew who
wants to do any מצווה, mitzvah, he gets reward, he actually he
does get reward doing any of the any of the תרי"ג מצוות,
613 mitzvot, like an אינו מצווה ועושה. eino metzuveh ve’oseh. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues. אלא כך אומרין, Ela kach omrin, this
is what the עובדי כוכבים avodei kochavim say to הקדוש ברוך הוא,
Hakadosh Baruch Hu, fine. So they can't basically say, hey, if you
would have given it to us, we would have fulfilled it, because
God just says, yeah, let's see what your track record is for
the שבע מצוות בני נח. sheva mitzvot bnei Noach. Okay, so fine,
here's what they say to God. ריבונו
של עולם, Ribono shel Olam, ישראל שקיבלוה היכן קיימוה? Yisrael shekibluah hechan
kiyamuah? So some take out the אלא כך אומרין ela kach omrin
like okay, they tried to argue with God, hey, you should have
done it to us, we would have given it, and God says
back, no, I'm sorry, your track record shows you wouldn't have done
it. So now they say like Michael said, alright, so you're saying
that we don't get credit because you didn't give it to us
because our track record shows we wouldn't have done it. The Jews
who got it, they didn't do it either. So why are they
getting so rewarded? Okay, היכן קיימוה? hechan kiyamuah? אמר להם הקדוש ברוך
הוא, Amar lahem Hakadosh Baruch Hu, so God says back, אני מעיד
בהם שקיימו את התורה כולה. ani me’id bahem shekiyamu et haTorah kulah.
I will testify that they established that they fulfilled the whole תורה.
Torah. אומרין לפניו, Omrin lefanav, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono shel Olam, כלום
יש אב שמעיד על בנו? klum yesh av sheme’id al bno? Your
פסול עדות. pasul edus. You're you're נוגע בדבר, noge’a b’davar, you have
a vested interest. You can't testify on your קרוב, karov, you can't
testify
on your child. You're showing favoritism, דכתיב d'ksiv בני בכורי ישראל. beni
bechori Yisrael. You've already showed favor for them, you gave them the
תורה. Torah. Okay, אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar lahem Hakadosh Baruch
Hu, שמים וארץ יעידו בהם. shamayim va'aretz ya’idu bahem. Fine, we’ll take
some impartial witnesses, heaven and earth,
like שמעו שמים, shimu shamayim, like ותעצר השמים, ve-tassar hashamayim, the heavens
are often used as האזינו השמים ואדברה, ha’azinu hashamayim ve’adabera, like is
often used as a way like to testify to an oath that
is being made or to hold people accountable. The heavens and earth
based on the rains
and the produce that will come from the earth, they are the
witnesses that hold people accountable. So they will testify שקיימו את התורה
כולה. shekiyamu et haTorah kulah. אומרין לפניו, Omrin lefanav, they say to
ריבונו של עולם, Ribono shel Olam, Master of the
Universe, שמים וארץ נוגעים בעדותם. shamayim va'aretz nog’im be-edutam. No, they're
also have a vested interest in it. Why? שנאמר Shene’emar אם לא
בריתי יומם ולילה, im lo briti yomam valayla, were it not for
my covenant of day and night, meaning the the covenant of the
תורה, Torah, חוקות שמים וארץ לא שמתי, chukot shamayim va'aretz lo samti,
I would not have created the laws of the heavens and earth.
What does that mean? דאמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש, D’amar Rabbi Shimon
ben Lakish, מאי דכתיב ויהי ערב ויהי בוקר יום השישי? mai d’ksiv
vayehi erev vayehi voker yom hashishi?
Why does it say the day of the sixth, not the sixth
day, not just יום שישי? yom shishi? What's the ה? hei? מלמד
שהתנה הקדוש ברוך הוא עם מעשה בראשית, Melamed shehishnah Hakadosh Baruch Hu
im ma'aseh bereshit, because the whole six days of creation were all
dependent on the sixth day, the sixth day of סיון, Sivan, the
day of the giving of the תורה. Torah. Okay, and all of
the acts of creation were it all was about that eventual day,
sixth day of סיון Sivan that would eventually come. ואמר, Ve-amar, and
said to them, אם ישראל מקבלים את התורה מוטב, im Yisrael mekablim
et haTorah mutav, if ultimately the whole reason for creation was for
the Jews to accept and keep the תורה Torah and if they
accept my תורה, Torah, then it’ll be good, ואם לאו אני אחזיר
אתכם לתהו ובוהו, ve-im lav ani achazir etchem l'tohu vavohu, if not
we’ll go back to the beginning, we’ll scrap the whole world, we’ll
go back to the to the to the vastness and desolateness that
preceded creation. So since God is saying that the heavens and the
earth are were created for the sake of the תורה, Torah, אם
לא בריתי יומם ולילה, im lo briti yomam valayla, and that the
acts of the creation were dependent on the Jews accepting and presumably
fulfilling the תורה. Torah. So since all of creation exists, that's a
very powerful statement as well. All creation exists for us to live
a life of for us to have accepted and live a life
of תורה Torah and if we're not doing that, then there's no
purpose to creation. But that's also why they can't testify that we've
done it, because if we haven't done it, then God's just gonna
scrap it all and go back to the beginning and the heavens
and earth will be destroyed. So they have a vested interest in
saying that we've done it. Yes.
Yeah, right, but this is sort of like a backhanded way of
attacking the premise. Oh, okay, your פסול עדות. pasul edus. What about
like I thought they'd be challenging God, what do you mean בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael kept the תורה? Torah? What about all the אלילים?
elilim? What about the עגל הזהב? egel ha-zahav?
Alright, Michael, this מדרש midrash is not interested in making that point,
okay? So let's keep on going. Okay, it is interested in making
the point that, and as I said, it all depends on your
perspective, right? Once you have some initial there's some word for this,
I forget what it's
called, structuring there's another psychological term, but anyway, but it's basically the
power of an initial bias. Once
you have an initial perspective, you organize all the information that's coming
in to fit that perspective, right? So if you think oh, all
the Jews keep the מצוות mitzvot and the תורה, Torah, okay, every
now and then it's true there were periods where they didn't or
whatever, those were aberrations, basically they always kept the תורה Torah and
the מצוות. mitzvot. And you say all the non-Jews
don't. What you decide is the rule and what you decide is
the exception, right, that makes all the difference. So the גמרא Gemara
here is not interested in in looking at the exceptions, what it's
framing as the exceptions. It is wants to frame it as no,
the rule is that ישראל Yisrael has led a life of keeping
תורה Torah and
מצוות. mitzvot. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so where were we? ואמר חזקיה מאי דכתיב, V'amar Chizkiyah mai de'chtiv,
what's meant משמים השמעת דין ארץ יראה ושקטה, Mishamayim hishmata din eretz
yerah v'shakata, from the heavens you have heard the judgment was heard,
the land sought or feared and was and was tranquil, was silence.
אם יראה למה שקטה, Im yerah lama shakata, if it feared why
did it become tranquil? ואם שקטה למה יראה, V'im shakata lama yerah,
and if it was tranquil why was it fearful? אלא בתחילה יראה
ולבסוף שקטה, Ela bitchila yerah u'l'sof shakata, in the beginning it was
fearful and in the end
because it was fearful that the Jews wouldn't keep the תורה Torah
and the מצוות, mitzvot, and then when it saw that they did
accept the תורה, Torah, then it was tranquil because now it won't
be destroyed because they accepted the תורה Torah at הר סיני. Har
Sinai. So heavens and earth can't testify, they are פסול לעדות. pasul
le'edus. Again notice it's all about a life of תורה Torah and
מצוות. mitzvot. That's why the world exists. It's not a life about
proclaiming the sense that there's one true transcendent God and idolatry is
false. The war is no longer about God versus idolatry. It's about
keeping a life of תורה Torah and מצוות mitzvot in a world
that there's a lot of temptations and things to pull you away.
And the whole culture outside is not a culture of תורה Torah
and מצוות. mitzvot. So it's very different how it's sort of framing
what does it mean to be a Jew among the nations in
the time of the Rabbis as opposed to what it meant in
biblical times.
It says,
אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar lei Hakadosh Baruch Hu, fine, you
can't use the heaven and earth as witnesses. So God said to
them, מכם יבואו ויעידו בהם בישראל, mikem yavo'u ve'ya'idu bahem b'Yisrael, fine,
you will come and testify. You can bear witness how the Jews
have led a life of keeping the תורה, Torah, יעידו בהם בישראל
שקיימו את התורה כולה. ya'idu bahem b'Yisrael shekiyemu haTorah kulah. יבוא
נמרוד Yavo Nimrod come, ויעיד באברהם שלא
עבד
עבודה כוכבים. ve'ya'id b'Avraham shelo avad avodah kochavim. Right, אברהם Avraham is
the מדרש Midrash right now in the פסוקים. psukim. אברהם Avraham wouldn't
at אור כשדים, Ur Kasdim, he was thrown into the fire because
he wouldn't worship idols. נמרוד Nimrod himself can testify to that.
יבוא לבן Yavo Lavan come, ויעיד ביעקב שלא נחשד על הגזל. ve'ya'id
b'Yaakov shelo nechshad al hagezel. לבן Lavan runs after יעקב Yaakov and
says, you know, you stole my תרפים terafim or whatever and he
says he looks around and יעקב Yaakov says, what, you haven't found
anything here. Like as רש"י Rashi says, not even a scissors, not
even a pin. Show me somebody who works for his employer for
20 years and doesn't even have like a paper cup from his
employer, and I have nothing. So לבן Lavan saw that. לבן Lavan
couldn't counter יעקב. Yaakov. And the irony of
that
that רחל Rachel did steal the תרפים, terafim, but יעקב Yaakov didn't.
Like as I said before, we're deciding, look, we're looking at anyway
the people we're choosing to look at, אברהם, Avraham, יעקב, Yaakov, like
how about, there's a lot of other people. How about, how many
of the בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael worshiped the עגל egel at the
foot of הר סיני? Har Sinai? Those are, we're not discussing
them. יבוא אשת פוטיפר ותעיד ביוסף שלא נחשד על עבירה. Yavo eshet
Potifar v'ta'id b'Yosef shelo nechshad al aveirah. How about the wife of
פוטיפר? Potifar? She can testify that she, he did not do sexual
sin. Now רש"י Rashi points out that what's interesting is that it's
actually also a little bit continuing the theme of the שבע מצוות.
Sheva Mitzvos. All of these,
אברהם, Avraham, יעקב, Yaakov, and יוסף Yosef lived prior to מתן תורה,
Matan Torah, therefore but the מצוות mitzvot that they're being upheld as
having fulfilled is the שבע מצוות בני נח, Sheva Mitzvot Bnei Noach,
right? Think about what we're talking about, עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, גזל,
gezel, and גילוי עריות. giluy arayot. So here it's saying when they
were only בני נח Bnei Noach they kept the בני נח Bnei
Noach and then we're going to get to when they were Jews.
Yes, they were all not Jewish or whatever, they're all people from
whatever is the other side that are supposed to testify, right? בני
נח? Bnei Noach?
Yeah, they're all non-Jews. The non-Jews are testifying. Right, exactly. You non-Jews
will testify that when ישראל Yisrael were still in the status of
בני נח, Bnei Noach, this is the way רש"י Rashi says this,
they were keeping the מצוות בני נח. mitzvot Bnei Noach. And let's
keep on
going post מתן תורה. Matan Torah. יבוא נבוכדנצר ויעיד בחנניה מישאל ועזריה
שלא השתחוו לצלם. Yavo Nevuchadnetzar v'ya'id b'Chananyah Mishael v'Azaryah shelo hishtachavu latzelem.
Let נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar come and testify that חנניה, Chananyah, מישאל, Mishael, and
עזריה Azaryah didn't bow down to the idol. יבוא דריוש ויעיד בדניאל
שלא ביטל את התפילה. Yavo Daryavesh v'ya'id b'Daniel shelo bitel et hatfillah.
Let דריוש Daryavesh come and testify for דניאל Daniel that he would,
he
prayed daily, it says in דניאל. Daniel. So תפילה tfillah is not
right, an interesting, like is that even a תורה Torah מצוה? mitzvah?
It's certainly not one of the שבע מצוות בני נח. Sheva Mitzvot
Bnei Noach. But now anyway, when they're in this period, the non-Jews
can go ahead and testify to the way the Jews kept the
תורה. Torah. Now תוספות Tosafos points out and the מהרש"א Maharsha elaborate
that השתחוו לצלם hishtachavu latzelem is not the same phrase as what
by אברהם Avraham it said that he wasn't עובד עבודה זרה. oved
avodah zarah. So תוספות Tosafos says... says that it could be that
the idol, that the statue that they were supposed to bow down
to חנניה מישאל ועזריה, Chananiah Mishael veAzaryah, was not even an idol.
It was just a statue, you know, to show fealty to נבוכדנצר
Nevuchadnezzar and so on, and it wasn't even an act of actual
idolatrous worship. And nevertheless, they chose to give up their lives rather
than to do that. So that would obviously be not just within
the seven מצות בני נח. mitzvot bnei noach. Of course, that's not
even commanded by הלכה halacha if it's not a real עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. So תוספות Tosfot actually becomes an important discussion in תוספות
Tosfot because, you know, תוספות Tosfot dealt with the fact about how
Jews in the Crusades gave up their lives, and can you have
an idea of martyrdom when it's not technically demanded by הלכה? halacha?
תוספות Tosfot is also bothered because the מדרש Midrash says that had
חנניה מישאל ועזריה Chananiah Mishael veAzaryah been tortured, they would have bowed
down. So תוספות Tosfot doesn't want to believe that if they had
been tortured they actually would have been עובד עבודה זרה, oveid avodah
zarah, you know. So תוספות Tosfot actually says, no, because it wasn't
real עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, that it was just a statue. Anyway,
but at this stage you're saying, you know, we're going beyond just,
possibly going beyond certainly by the תפילה, tefilah, we're going beyond just
the seven Noachide מצות. mitzvot. We're after the period of מתן תורה.
matan torah. And then יבא בלדד השוחי וצופר הנעמתי ואליפז התימני, yavo
Bildad HaShuchi veTzofar HaNaamati veEliphaz HaTeimani, which were all like, you know,
the colleagues of איוב Iyov there, and understood to be prophets, so
there, and let them יעידו בעם ישראל שקימו התורה כלה, yaidu beAm
Yisrael shekiyemu haTorah kula, let them testify. Now of course the funny
thing is, as opposed to all these other stories, they weren't present
when the Jews were keeping the תורה, Torah, but the idea is,
is that these are like non-Jewish prophets who can through their prophecy
like report back and tell you guys that then, you know, and
testify that the Jewish people have kept the life of תורה. Torah.
שנאמר, sheneemar, as the verse says, יתנו עדיהם ויצדקו, yitnu edeihem veyitzdaku,
I think it is. Okay, so let them give their testimony and
be found righteous. So again, in the original verse, we're going back
to the verse in ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. This is about a challenge to
the idolaters. Let's see you go ahead and prove your righteousness, right,
it's about showing the falsehood of idolatry, but here it's all being
reframed as not about idolatry, but about who kept the life of
תורה Torah and מצות. mitzvot. And you yourselves will come and testify
that the Jewish people kept the life of תורה Torah and מצות.
mitzvot. אמרו לפניו, amru lefanav, they said to him, רבונו של עולם,
Ribbono Shel Olam, Master of the Universe, תנה לנו מראש ונעשנה. tenah
lanu merosh venaasena. Give us one last chance. Okay, yes, it's the
end of days, yes, you know, but come on, give us one
last chance. Now we see the truth. אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא,
amar lahem HaKadosh Baruch Hu, שוטים שבעולם, shotim shebaolam, idiots! מי שטרח
בערב שבת יאכל בשבת. mi shetarach beerev Shabbos yochal beShabbos. If you
worked on Friday, you get to eat on
שבת. Shabbos. מי שלא טרח בערב שבת מהיכן יאכל בשבת? mi shelo
tarach beerev Shabbos meheichan yochal beShabbos? Where can you eat on שבת,
Shabbos, right? This the world to come is like שבת, Shabbat, because
it is a time to reap the rewards, but you can't do
any מצות. mitzvot. You can't do any, you know, any work. The
work you do has to precede and then you're able to reap
the rewards when you come to the שבת. Shabbat. שבת Shabbat is
a time when we're no longer for us toiling and in the
sort of sense of עולם הבא olam haba where it's no longer
even a time to be doing מצות. mitzvot. It's just to be
reward you know sort of benefiting from the work that was done
prior. Okay, so אלא אף על פי כן, ella af al pi
kein, even though you really have no legitimate claim, the time when
you were supposed to have done it you did not do it,
okay, and now it should be too
late. מצוה קלה יש לי. mitzvah kalah yesh li. I got a
very easy מצוה. mitzvah. Let's see how well you do with it.
וסוכה שמה, vesukkah shemah, it's called a סוכה. Sukkah. לכו ועשו אותה.
lechu veasu osah. Go do it, let's see how well you do.
Okay, this might be obviously following the whole point that, you know,
in the פסוקים pesukim in of which is the which is the
נביא? navi? Is it where it speaks where it speaks about that
that we read on סוכות Succot that all the nations will come
לחוג את חג הסוכות? lachog et chag hasukkot?
That's the הפטרה Haftorah that we read, right? What's that הפטרה? Haftorah?
אשר לא יעלה לחוג את חג הסוכות? asher lo yaaleh lachog et
chag hasukkot? Nobody knows what I'm talking about. No,
nobody pays attention to the הפטרה. Haftorah.
What?
Not since my דאוון... davin... I was going to say זכריה Zechariah
or...
Here wait, wait, here we go,
סוכות, Succot, זכריה, Zechariah, I think.
זכריה. Zechariah. Who said זכריה? Zechariah?
You get two points. Excellent.
Let's see if that's it.
Yep, that was it, extra points for מיכל. Michal. Okay, so והיה
כל הנותר מכל הגוים הבאים על ירושלים ועלו מדי שנה בשנה להשתחות
למלך ה' צבאות ולחוג את חג הסוכות. vehayah kol hanotar mikol hagoyim
habaim al Yerushalayim vealu midei shanah beshanah lehishtachavot leMelech Hashem Tzevaot velachog
et chag hasukkot. והיה אשר לא יעלה מאת משפחות הארץ אל ירושלים
להשתחות למלך ה' צבאות ולא עליהם יהיה הגשם. vehayah asher lo yaaleh
meet mishpachot haaretz el Yerushalayim lehishtachavot leMelech Hashem Tzevaot velo aleihem yihyeh
hageshem. Okay, and if you don't come up to do this, then
you won't get the rain. ואם משפחת מצרים לא תעלה ולא באה
ולא עליהם תהיה המגפה אשר יגוף ה' את הגוים אשר לא יעלו
לחוג את חג הסוכות. veim mishpachat Mitzrayim lo taaleh velo vaah velo
aleihem tiyeh hamageifah asher yigof Hashem et hagoyim asher lo yaalu lachog
et chag hasukkot. So actually here you have the vision of this
in the Messianic
period, the one thing that they're going to be doing, we're going
to see if they're going to do is to come up to
ירושלים Yerushalayim and celebrate. Celebrate סוכות, Sukkot, maybe because סוכות Sukkot has
a universalist dimension, it's about rain and so on, okay, so we're
going this is the one מצוה, mitzvah, let's see how well you
do with it. Okay, so לכו ואצבוטו. Lechu ve'atzvutu. ומי מצית אמרת
הכי? Umi matzit amart hachi? Now, how could they actually make that
claim that they want one last chance? ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי,
Ve'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, מאי דכתיב? mai dichteiv? What's meant by
אשר אנכי מצוך היום? asher anochi metzavcha hayom? That I command you
today. היום לעשותם ולא למחר לעשותם. Hayom la'asotam velo lemachar la'asotam. Today
you do it, don't do it in the future period in the,
you know, עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. היום לעשותם Hayom la'asotam ולא
היום ליטול שכרכם. velo hayom litol secharchem. Today you do it but
you don't get rewarded, you'll get reward later. So again, it's sort
of like repeating the point that the מדרש Midrash itself said earlier,
which is that, you know, מי שלא טרח בערב שבת מהיכן יאכל
בשבת. mi shelo tarach be'erev Shabbat me'eichan yochal beShabbat. But the גמרא
Gemara sort
of says, says,
I still don't get why God is giving them a chance, right?
עולם הבא Olam HaBa is not the time to be doing מצוות
mitzvot and reaping, you know, and getting reward for those מצוות. mitzvot.
You have to do the מצוות mitzvot in this world. So אלא,
ella, you're right. You know, there is no logic. They should not
get that chance. אלא שאין הקדוש ברוך הוא בא בטרוניא עם בריותיו.
Ella she'ein HaKadosh Baruch Hu ba bitrunya im briyotav. God does not
want to come with some type of a like,
a what? Complaint, right. Like, or he wants to get or what's
more like is he wants to make it like he's above the
ability for them to have any complaints. How do they translate that?
Excuses, with any excuses. Yeah, like, you know, you want to sort
of just like eliminate any possible basis for any complaint. I'm going
to act in a way that you would have that, you know,
gives you even a chance you don't deserve so you cannot come
with any complaints against me. Okay, so ואמאי קרי ליה מצוה קלה?
Ve'amai kari lei mitzvah kalah? Why is it called a מצוה קלה?
mitzvah kalah? משום דלית ביה חסרון כיס mishum deleit bei chisron kis
because it doesn't cost any money. I mean, I don't know, you
still have to build a סוכה sukkah and pay for the raw
materials, but whatever. מיד כל אחד ואחד נוטל והולך ועושה סוכה בראש
גגו. Miyad kol echad ve'echad notel veholech ve'oseh sukkah berosh gago. Everybody
says, great, and they go and they put a סוכה sukkah on
their rooftops. והקדוש ברוך הוא מקדיר עליהם חמה מתקופת תמוז VeHaKadosh Baruch
Hu makdir aleihem chamah mitkufat Tammuz and God makes the sun shine
on them in this while it's still the summertime. I wonder some
גרסאות girsa'ot have כיתקופת תמוז kitkufat Tammuz like the summertime, but anyway
our גרסא girsa is during the summertime while it's still the summer
period. וכל אחד ואחד מבעט בסוכתו ויוצא. Vekol echad ve'echad meva'et besukkato
veyozei. And then everybody kicks their סוכה sukkah and says, ach, this
is stupid, and leaves. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as it says, and this is
why we maybe also why we wanted to do סוכה sukkah because
we wanted to tie it into this verse, ננתקה את מוסרותימו, Nenatkah
et moseroteimo, let us release ourselves from the bonds, from his bonds,
ונשליכה ממנו עבותימו venashlichah mimenu avoteimo and cast off from us again
our like bonds. So somehow because סוכה sukkah is like, you know,
is like something you tie together the סכך sechach and the walls,
and also the מהרש"א Maharsha says like עבות avot might be a
play on the word ענף עץ עבות, anaf etz avot, right? So
anyway, so we cast it all off, forget this, this is who
needs this.
So so there now before the גמרא Gemara can sort of end
the מדרש, Midrash, there's a lot of interruptions in this מדרש. Midrash.
The גמרא Gemara waits one minute, how did that make sense? מקדיר,
Makdir, God caused the sun to come burning down. ואמרת אין הקדוש
ברוך הוא בא בטרוניא עם בריותיו. Ve'amarta ein HaKadosh Baruch Hu ba
bitrunya im briyotav.
You want to be above any possible complaint and here he is,
he's making it hard for them. He's not giving them a fair
chance. So גמרא Gemara says, no, משום דישראל נמי זימני דמימשכא להו
תקופת תמוז עד חגא. mishum deYisrael nami zimni demimshacha lehu tkufat Tammuz
ad chaga. Sometimes for us also it's still summer while it is
סוכות Sukkot based on, you know, how the lunar and the solar
calendar correspond, we might be still in the summer months while it
is סוכות. Sukkot. Okay, I mean for that to be, it would
have to be that סוכות Sukkot would have to fall out in
August. I don't know if סוכות Sukkot does ever fall out in
August. But anyway, okay anyway, so nevertheless meaning sometimes the Jews also
have to deal with this and they don't go kick their סוכה.
sukkah. So God wasn't giving them an undue challenge, he wanted to
see, would you be able to do it in a normal difficult
situation, where we know that the Jews have been able to do
it, okay? Of course, you know, maybe they haven't built up their
muscle for it yet. It's still unfair, right? You don't give somebody
who's just starting the hardest challenge. Anyway, והא דלמי הצטערה, veha delamei
itzta'ara,
and so it's also true for the Jews so it wasn't an
unfair challenge. So גמרא Gemara says ואמר רבא מצטער פטור מן הסוכה.
ve'amar Rava mitzta'er patur min hasukkah. So what's the big deal though?
If they're, if it's uncomfortable they are free to leave their סוכה.
sukkah. So נו הי דפטור, nu hai depatur, fine you're exempt, but
בעוטי מי מבעטי? be'utei mi meba'atei? You don't kick your סוכה sukkah
when you're leaving. Okay, so you know, that reflects the idea that
not that they're just saying oh you know we don't have to
הלכתית halachically or whatever, that reflects the idea that they are completely,
you know, non-disposed, you know,
constitutionally, you know, not given to what it means to live this
type of a life and as soon as things get hard they
get frustrated and they reject it and so on. That's again how
it's being framed. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says מיד, miyad,
by the way you're again you sort of heat, know, or talking
about what impression this is creating, how it's framing looking at the
non-Jews. So after it basically sort of dismisses their accomplishment and says
like even if you see things that they're doing they're not really,
it's like אינם מצווים ועושים, einam metzuvim ve'osim, they don't really get
so much reward. Right here it's also basically sort of making a
like a more characteristic claim. You know what, they're not up for
this type of a life anyway. Only Jews are really up for
living a type of a regimented, regulated life, type of a life,
you know. So it's again sort of like very much coloring a
whole way of looking at, you know, non-Jews. So it's not just
that they don't happen to observe it, like even when given a
last chance, even an easy thing, like it's you know, it's they're
incapable of this. All right, so that's you know, it's funny and
whatever, funny and sad. It's
it's important that that's the opening, you know sort of דרשה drasha
in this of the מסכת. masechet. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, מיד הקדוש ברוך הוא יושב ומשחק עליהם. Miyad Hakadosh
Baruch Hu yoshev umesachek aleihem. So then God starts laughing at them.
Haha, what silly nations of the world. Okay, so שנאמר יושב בשמים
ישחק, Shene'emar Yoshev Bashamayim Yischak, this is the end of that verse
about let's cast off our bonds, the one who lives up in
heaven will laugh. אמר רבי יצחק אין שחוק לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא
אלא אותו היום בלבד. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak ein schok lifnei HaKadosh Baruch
Hu ela oto hayom bilvad. The only day that God ever laughs
will laugh is that one day in the future time when all
of the non-Jews' defense of their actions and their attempt to try
to do מצוות mitzvot is all shown to be total folly. So
איכא דמתני להא דרבי יצחק אהא. Ika dematni leha d'Rabbi Yitzchak aha.
Now some teach it on the following teaching. תניא רבי יוסי אומר
לעתיד לבוא באין עובדי כוכבים ומתגיירין. Tanya Rabbi Yosi omer le'atid lavo
ba'in ovdei kochavim umitgayrin. In the future time, maybe not in, you
know, when in the Messianic period they'll come they'll want to convert.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ומי מקבלינן מינייהו? Umi mekabelinan mineihu? But
would we accept them? והתניא אין מקבלין גרים לימות המשיח. Vehatanya ein
mekabelin gerim limot Hamashiach. We won't don't accept converts at the Messianic
period because then they're not doing it for the right reasons. They're
just doing it because they want to receive the reward and be
part of Israel. כיוצא בו לא קיבלו גרים לא בימי דוד ולא
בימי שלמה. Keyotze bo lo kiblu gerim lo bimei David velo bimei
Shlomo. Similarly we didn't accept converts in the time of David and
Shlomo because it was too good and we didn't think people were
sincere. אלא, Ela, fine, שנעשו גרים גרורים. shena'asu gerim grurim. We won't
accept them, but they will be sort of like they'll be it's
alliterative, גרים גרורים, gerim grurim, but לגרורים legrurim like
to drag on converts, meaning they'll convert themselves and they'll present themselves
as converts and try to be accepted as converts even if they
are not formally accepted, you know, by the court. ומניחין, Umenichin,
and to show how that they're Jewish, they'll put on the classic
signs of Jewish identity, or at least male Jewish identity. ומניחין תפילין
בראשיהן ותפילין בזרועותיהן, Umenichin tefillin berosheihen utefillin bizro'oteihen, תפילין tefillin on their
heads and on their arms, ציצית בבגדיהן, tzitzit bevigdeihen, and ציצית tzitzit
on their garments, ומזוזה בפתחיהן, umezuzah befitchaihen, and a מזוזה mezuzah on
their doors. כיון שרואים מלחמת גוג ומגוג, Keivan shero'im milchemet Gog uMagog,
but then they see the wars of גוג ומגוג Gog uMagog are
approaching and, you know, and the Jewish people are now they're are
being threatened because it's the wars of גוג ומגוג. Gog uMagog. It's
interesting, it's enough Messianic period and things are so good enough that
they want to join the Jews, but the wars of גוג ומגוג
Gog uMagog haven't come. You normally assume that the Messianic period follows
the wars of גוג ומגוג, Gog uMagog, so anyway, interesting trying to
figure out the timeline. Okay, ואומר להן, Ve'omer lahen, על מה באתם?
al mah batem? And, you know, so they the these גרים gerim
will say, you know,
to the the nations that are coming in the wars of גוג
ומגוג, Gog uMagog, why are you coming? ואומרים לו על השם ועל
משיחו. Ve'omrim lo al Hashem ve'al Meshicho. We're coming to fight against
God and against the Messiah. שנאמר למה רגשו גוים ולאומים יהגו ריק,
Shene'emar lamah rageshu goyim ule'umim yehgu rik, again
quoting from the same פרק perek of תהלים. Tehillim. Okay, so now
they see, oh my God, the
the armies of גוג ומגוג Gog uMagog are about to attack the
Jewish people and here I was, I was connecting myself to the
Jewish people, I better ditch this. So מיד, Miyad, so וכל אחד
ואחד מנתק מצותיו והולך. vechol echad ve'echad menatek mitzvotav veholech.
Everyone now rejects the מצוות mitzvot like it's fair weather friends. You
see that like I guess the fair weather was also by סוכה,
Sukkah, right? You see that things are about to be bad, they
leave it. שנאמר ננתקה את מוסרותימו ונשליכה ממנו עבותימו. Shene'emar nenatkah et
mosroteimo venashlichah mimenu avoteimo. You know, תוספות Tosafot here points out that
the מוסרותימו, mosroteimo, the bonds, the ropes, are also like the תפילין,
tefillin, like the תפילין tefillin is sort of being, you know, wrapped
around. And the עבותימו, avoteimo, the braided, is the ציצית, tzitzit, right?
So the תפילין tefillin and the ציצית tzitzit are now the ropes
and the braids. Okay, anyway, they cast it all off. והקדוש ברוך
הוא יושב ומשחק, VehaKadosh Baruch Hu yoshev umesachek, and then God sits
up in heaven and laughs. שנאמר יושב בשמים ישחק. Shene'emar Yoshev Bashamayim
Yischak. אמר רבי יצחק אין לו להקדוש ברוך הוא שחוק אלא אותו
היום בלבד. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak ein lo leHaKadosh Baruch Hu schok ela
oto hayom bilvad. God has no laughter except that day. איני, Aini,
is that really true? ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב שתים עשרה שעות
הוי היום. Ve'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav shteim esreh sha'ot havei hayom.
The day can be divided into twelve hours. שלוש ראשונות הקדוש ברוך
הוא יושב ועוסק בתורה. Shalosh rishonot HaKadosh Baruch Hu yoshev ve'osek baTorah.
The first three hours, God sits and learns תורה. Torah. שניות, Shniyot,
the next set of three hours, from, you know, from what is
it, from nine to twelve, יושב ודן את כל העולם כולו. yoshev
vedan et kol ha'olam kulo. He sits in judgment of the world,
כולו. kulo. כיון שרואה שנתחייב עולם כליה, Keivan shero'eh shenitchayev olam kelayah,
once he sees that the world is not does not merit and
deserves destruction, right? because, מיד עומד מכסא הדין ויושב על כסא רחמים.
Miyad omed mikise hadin veyoshev al kise rachamim.
He goes from the seat of judgment to the seat of compassion,
the world has to continue going. שלישיות, Shlishiyot, the third set of
the three hours, from twelve to three p.m., יושב וזן את כל
העולם כולו. yoshev vezan et kol ha'olam kulo.
He sustains the world, he provides sustenance for the world.
מקרני ראמים עד ביצי כינים, Mikarnei re'eimim ad beitzei kinim, from the
horns of at some point explained as a
mythical beast like a
unicorn. What do they say? It says a tall beast with beautiful
horns. Suggested reindeer. Reindeer. Okay, from the
reindeer to the to the to the eggs of lice, okay, you
know, from the most lofty of animals to the smallest of animals,
God provides.
For what purpose he feeds the eggs of lice?
Like what, why do eggs of lice need to eat? So Rashi
says ביצי כינים beitzai kinim is not actually eggs of lice. Rashi
says it's some type of an animal, because I think Rashi was
bothered with that. But I think the simple sense is like from
the most lofty to the most tiny, you know. Anyway, it says
it's a species of lice. Right, a species called it's a species
of lice, they're following Rashi. Anyway, God sustains the world. רביעיות, revi'ot,
the fourth set of three hours, from 3 PM to 6 PM,
יושב ומשחק עם לויתן, yoshev u-mesachek im livyatan, you know, God needs
his entertainment so he doesn't have TV and he doesn't have whatever
computer games, so what he does is he goes and he sports
with the Leviathan, which is a little bit too anthropomorphic for me
if you ask me. It seems sounds a little pagan. Anyway, שנאמר,
she-ne'emar, as it says, לויתן זה יצרת לשחק בו, livyatan zeh yatzarta
lisachak bo, the Leviathan you created to sort of play with. So
so ah you see God God laughs, you know, every day. So
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק: Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak: עם בריותיו
משחק. im briyotav mesachek. No, you know the thing is are you
laughing with me or you laughing at me? So so every day
God laughs with his creatures. He takes pleasure in his creatures, right?
על בריותיו אינו משחק. al briyotav eino mesachek.
He doesn't laugh about his creatures. He doesn't mock and laugh, you
know, you're not laughing at. Only this one time at the end
of times when all of the claims of the non-Jews are shown
to be folly, then God laughs at them, not with them. Okay?
על בריותיו... al briyotav... okay, ועל בריותיו אינו משחק אלא אותו יום
בלבד. ve-al briyotav eino mesachek ela oto yom bilvad. Except that day.
אמרי ליה רב אחא לרב נחמן בר יצחק,
Amarei lei Rav Acha
le-Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, so Rav Acha said to Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak: מיום שחרב בית המקדש אין שחוק לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא. mi-yom
she-charav Beit ha-Mikdash ein s'chok lifnei HaKadosh Baruch Hu. Actually
from the day that the בית המקדש Beit ha-Mikdash was destroyed, you're
saying that God like sort of plays with the לויתן livyatan and
takes pleasure and laughs, but from the day the בית המקדש Beit
ha-Mikdash was destroyed God no longer laughs. He's no longer takes pleasure.
ומנלן דליכא שחוק? u-minalan de-leika s'chok?
Where do you know this from? אילימא ממה דכתיב: i-leima mi-ma de-chtiv:
ויקרא ה׳ אלוקים צבאות ביום ההוא לבכי ולמספד ולקרחה. Vayikra Hashem Elokim
Tzeva'ot bayom hahu livchi u-lemisped u-lekorchah. That day would be called a
day of crying and you know and eulogizing and and tearing whatever
balding. דילמא ההוא יומא ותו לא? dilma hahu yoma ve-tulo lo?
Maybe it only means that day of the destruction, not for all
future time? אלא דכתיב, ela di-chtiv, because the verse says: אם אשכחך
ירושלים תשכח ימיני תדבק לשוני לחכי אם לא אזכרכי. im eshkachech Yerushalayim
tishkach yemini tidbak leshoni le-chiki im lo ezkerechi. So
you know I if I forget you, you know, well you know
let my right hand be forgotten, which shows that the the mourning
of Jerusalem continues forever. So גמרא Gemara says: מיום שכחה הוא
דליכא, mi-yom she-shich'cha hu de-leika, okay, so God won't forget Jerusalem, אבל
שחוק מי איכא? aval s'chok mi-ika? Doesn't mean you can't have, you
know, can't enjoy life? Right? And God can't get pleasure, you know,
and laughs just because you're always keeping ירושלים, Yerushalayim, even at a
wedding we remember ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it doesn't mean we can't rejoice. אלא
מהא, ela me-ha, from here: החשיתי מעולם אחריש אתאפק. Hechesheiti me-olam acharish
et'apak.
Will I be silent from, you know, will I forever, you know,
hold back? So the end of the פסוק, pasuk, I should have
looked it up, but the end of the פסוק, pasuk, what does
it quote there, the end of the פסוק, pasuk, David?
Just says it's where it's from, Isaiah. Okay.
Anyway, so God will never be silent about the destruction of Jerusalem.
So now that God will always no longer laughs, you know, even
with his creatures, what does he do from 3 to 6 PM?
So ברביעית מאי עביד? birvi'it mai avid? What did he do in
this fourth quarter? יושב ומלמד תינוקות של בית רבן תורה. yoshev u-melamed
tinokot shel beit raban Torah. He sits and he teaches Torah to
the to the school children. Now the school children here what do
you mean? Why do we need God? Aren't they going to school?
So the point is these are infants that died at a young
age. So they're up in heaven and God is teaching them Torah.
It's a very beautiful image, right? God forbid, you know, an infant
dies, they're up in heaven being taught Torah by God. שנאמר, she-ne'emar,
את מי יורה דעה? et mi yoreh dei'ah? Who will teach knowledge?
ואת מי יבין שמועה? ve-et mi yavin shmu'ah? גמולי מחלב, g'mulei me-chalav,
those who have been weaned from milk, עתיקי משדים, atikei mi-shadayim, ripped
away from the breast, you know, because they died at a young
age. למי יורה דעה ולמי יבין שמועה? le-mi yoreh dei'ah u-lemi yavin
shmu'ah? To whom will God teach Torah, to whom will God, you
know, you know, make this heard? גמולי מחלב ועתיקי משדים. g'mulei me-chalav
ve-atikei mi-shadayim. God is teaching them Torah up in heaven. ומעקרא מן
הוה מגמר להו? u-mei-ikara man hava nigmar lehu? So before while there
was a בית המקדש Beit ha-Mikdash and God was spending that time
playing with the לויתן, livyatan, who was teaching these infants Torah? איבעית
אימא מטטרון, ei-ba'it eima Metatron, either it's מטטרון Metatron who was a
major angel was sort of seen to some degree as almost a
manifestation of God, separate discussion, ואיבעית אימא, ve-ei-ba'it eima, and if you
want, הא בהא עביד. ha-ba ha-avid. Beforehand God was doing both. He
was both teaching Torah and playing with the לויתן, livyatan, now he
just teaches Torah. Okay, ובלילה, u-balailah, that's just two more minutes. Now
what does God do at night once we're on this topic? ובלילה
מאי עביד? uve-layla mai avid? Now what does God do at night
once we're on this topic? איבעית אימא ibayit eima מעין יממא, me-ein
yamama, either he does activities somewhat parallel in what he does during
the day, ואיבעית אימא ve-ibayit eima if you want I could say
רכיב על כרוב קל שלו ושט. rochev al kruv kal shelo veshat.
God gets on his nice his light cherub and takes you know
flies through the world again a little anthropomorphic for me here, you
know take surveys the whole world בשמונה עשר אלף עולמות bishmonah asar
elef olamot or he goes into the 18,000 worlds that God has
created not just this world. שנאמר shenemar רכב
אלהים רבותים, rechev elohim ribotayim, God rides on רבותים, ribotayim, רבותים ribotayim
is 20,000, אלפי שנאן. alfei shinan. So אל תקרי al tikrei שנאן
shinan אלא ela שאינם she-einam מה? ma? It's 2,000 are not, meaning
20,000 minus 2,000, 18,000. So God takes a tour through his 18,000
worlds. ואיבעית אימא ve-ibayit eima יושב ושומע שירה מפי חיות, yoshev veshome'a
shira mipi chayot, God sits and hears the heavenly beasts you know
singing songs, שנאמר shenemar יומם
יצוה ה' חסדו, yomam yetzaveh Hashem chasdo, in the day God will
command his kindness ובלילה שירו עמי uvelayla shiro imi and in the
night his song is with me. Okay so I guess we will
end here for today.